if the reasoner delights in conflict and strife. Can reason force the reasoner to want less cruelty and waste? RNG: All on its own, the answer is no, but it doesn't take much to switch it to yes. You need two conditions: The first is that reasoners all care about their own well-being. That's one of the passions that has to be present in order for reason to go to work, and it's obviously present in all of us. We all care passionately about our own well-being. The second condition is that reasoners are members of a community of reasoners who can affect one another's well-being, can exchange messages, and comprehend each other's reasoning. And that's certainly true of our gregarious and loquatious species, well endowed with the instinct for language. SP: Well, that sounds good in theory, but has it worked that way in practice? In particular, can it explain a momentous historical development that I spoke about five years ago here at TED? Namely, we seem to be getting more humane. Centuries ago, our ancestors would burn cats alive as a form of popular entertainment. Knights waged constant war on each other by trying to kill as many of each other's peasants as possible. Governments executed people for frivolous reasons, like stealing a cabbage or criticizing the royal garden. The executions were designed to be as prolonged and as painful as possible, like crucifixion, disembowelment, breaking on the wheel. Respectable people kept slaves. For all our flaws, we have abandoned these barbaric practices. RNG: So, do you think it's human nature that's changed? SP: Not exactly. I think we still harbor instincts that can erupt in violence, like greed, tribalism, revenge, dominance, sadism. But we also have instincts that can steer us away, like self-control, empathy, a sense of fairness, what Abraham Lincoln called the better angels of our nature. RNG: So if human nature didn't change, what invigorated those better angels? SP: Well, among other things, our circle of empathy expanded. Years ago, our ancestors would feel the pain only of their family and people in their village. But with the expansion of literacy and travel, people started to sympathize with wider and wider circles, the clan, the tribe, the nation, the race, and perhaps eventually, all of humanity. RNG: Can hard-headed scientists really give so much credit to soft-hearted empathy? SP: They can and do. Neurophysiologists have found neurons in the brain that respond to other people's actions the same way they respond to our own. Empathy emerges early in life, perhaps before the age of one. Books on empathy have become bestsellers, like "The Empathic Civilization" and "The Age of Empathy." RNG: I'm all for empathy. I mean, who isn't? But all on its own, it's a feeble instrument for making moral progress. For one thing, it's innately biased toward blood relations, babies and warm, fuzzy animals. As far as empathy is concerned, ugly outsiders can go to hell. And even our best attempts to work up sympathy for those who are unconnected with us fall miserably short, a sad truth about human nature that was pointed out by Adam Smith. Adam Smith: Let us suppose that the great empire of China was suddenly swallowed up by an earthquake, and let us consider how a man of humanity in Europe would react on receiving intelligence of this dreadful calamity. He would, I imagine, first of all express very strongly his sorrow for the misfortune of that unhappy people. He would make many melancholy reflections upon the precariousness of human life, and when all these humane sentiments had been once fairly expressed, he would pursue his business or his pleasure with the same ease and tranquility as if no such accident had happened. If he was to lose his little finger tomorrow, he would not sleep tonight, but provided he never saw them, he would snore with the most profound security over the ruin of a hundred million of his brethren. SP: But if empathy wasn't enough to make us more humane, what else was there? RNG: Well, you didn't mention what might be one of our most effective better angels: reason. Reason has muscle. It's reason that provides the push to widen that circle of empathy. Every one of the humanitarian developments that you mentioned originated with thinkers who gave reasons for why some practice was indefensible. They demonstrated that the way people treated some particular group of others was logically inconsistent with the way they insisted on being treated themselves. SP: Are you saying that reason can actually change people's minds? Don't people just stick with whatever conviction serves their interests or conforms to the culture that they grew up in? RNG: Here's a fascinating fact about us: Contradictions bother us, at least when we're forced to confront them, which is just another way of saying that we are susceptible to reason. And if you look at the history of moral progress, you can trace a direct pathway from reasoned arguments to changes in the way that we actually feel. Time and again, a thinker would lay out an argument as to why some practice was indefensible, irrational, inconsistent with values already held. Their essay would go viral, get translated into many languages, get debated at pubs and coffee houses and salons, and at dinner parties, and influence leaders, legislators, popular opinion. Eventually their conclusions get absorbed into the common sense of decency, erasing the tracks of the original argument that had gotten us there. Few of us today feel any need to put forth a rigorous philosophical argument as to why slavery is wrong or public hangings or beating children. By now, these things just feel wrong. But just those arguments had to be made, and they were, in centuries past. SP: Are you saying that people needed a step-by-step argument to grasp why something might be a wee bit wrong with burning heretics at the stake? RNG: Oh, they did. Here's the French theologian Sebastian Castellio making the case. Sebastian Castellio: Calvin says that he's certain, and other sects say that they are. Who shall be judge? If the matter is certain, to whom is it so? To Calvin? But then, why does he write so many books about manifest truth? In view of the uncertainty, we must define heretics simply as one with whom we disagree. And if then we are going to kill heretics, the logical outcome will be a war of extermination, since each is sure of himself. SP: Or with hideous punishments like breaking on the wheel? RNG: The prohibition in our constitution of cruel and unusual punishments was a response to a pamphlet circulated in 1764 by the Italian jurist Cesare Beccaria. Cesare Beccaria: As punishments become more cruel, the minds of men, which like fluids always adjust to the level of the objects that surround them, become hardened, and after a hundred years of cruel punishments, breaking on the wheel causes no more fear than imprisonment previously did. For a punishment to achieve its objective, it is only necessary that the harm that it inflicts outweighs the benefit that derives from the crime, and into this calculation ought to be factored the certainty of punishment and the loss of the good that the commission of the crime will produce. Everything beyond this is superfluous, and therefore tyrannical. SP: But surely antiwar movements depended on mass demonstrations and catchy tunes by folk singers and wrenching photographs of the human costs of war. RNG: No doubt, but modern anti-war movements reach back to a long chain of thinkers who had argued as to why we ought to mobilize our emotions against war, such as the father of modernity, Erasmus. Erasmus: The advantages derived from peace diffuse themselves far and wide, and reach great numbers, while in war, if anything turns out happily, the advantage redounds only to a few, and those unworthy of reaping it. One man's safety is owing to the destruction of another. One man's prize is derived from the plunder of another. The cause of rejoicings made by one side is to the other a cause of mourning. Whatever is unfortunate in war, is severely so indeed, and whatever, on the contrary, is called good fortune, is a savage and a cruel good fortune, an ungenerous happiness deriving its existence from another's woe. SP: But everyone knows that the movement to abolish slavery depended on faith and emotion. It was a movement spearheaded by the Quakers, and it only became popular when Harriet Beecher Stowe's novel "Uncle Tom's Cabin" became a bestseller. RNG: But the ball got rolling a century before. John Locke bucked the tide of millennia that had regarded the practice as perfectly natural. He argued that it was inconsistent with the principles of rational government. John Locke: Freedom of men under government is to have a standing rule to live by common to everyone of that society and made by the legislative power erected in it, a liberty to follow my own will in all things where that rule prescribes not, not to be subject to the inconstant, uncertain, unknown, arbitrary will of another man, as freedom of nature is to be under no other restraint but the law of nature. SP: Those words sound familiar. Where have I read them before? Ah, yes. Mary Astell: If absolute sovereignty be not necessary in a state, how comes it to be so in a family? Or if in a family, why not in a state? Since no reason can be alleged for the one that will not hold more strongly for the other, if all men are born free, how is it that all women are born slaves, as they must be if being subjected to the inconstant, uncertain, unknown, arbitrary will of men be the perfect condition of slavery? RNG: That sort of co-option is all in the job description of reason. One movement for the expansion of rights inspires another because the logic is the same, and once that's hammered home, it becomes increasingly uncomfortable to ignore the inconsistency. In the 1960s, the Civil Rights Movement inspired the movements for women's rights, children's rights, gay rights and even animal rights. But fully two centuries before, the Enlightenment thinker Jeremy Bentham had exposed the indefensibility of customary practices such as the cruelty to animals. Jeremy Bentham: The question is not, can they reason, nor can they talk, but can they suffer? RNG: And the persecution of homosexuals. JB: As to any primary mischief, it's evident that it produces no pain in anyone. On the contrary, it produces pleasure. The partners are both willing. If either of them be unwilling, the act is an offense, totally different in its nature of effects. It's a personal injury. It's a kind of rape. As to the any danger exclusive of pain, the danger, if any, much consist in the tendency of the example. But what is the tendency of this example? To dispose others to engage in the same practices. But this practice produces not pain of any kind to anyone. SP: Still, in every case, it took at least a century for the arguments of these great thinkers to trickle down and infiltrate the population as a whole. It kind of makes you wonder about our own time. Are there practices that we engage in where the arguments against them are there for all to see but nonetheless we persist in them? RNG: When our great grandchildren look back at us, will they be as appalled by some of our practices as we are by our slave-owning, heretic-burning, wife-beating, gay-bashing ancestors? SP: I'm sure everyone here could think of an example. RNG: I opt for the mistreatment of animals in factory farms. SP: The imprisonment of nonviolent drug offenders and the toleration of rape in our nation's prisons. RNG: Scrimping on donations to life-saving charities in the developing world. SP: The possession of nuclear weapons. RNG: The appeal to religion to justify the otherwise unjustifiable, such as the ban on contraception. SP: What about religious faith in general? RNG: Eh, I'm not holding my breath. SP: Still, I have become convinced that reason is a better angel that deserves the greatest credit for the moral progress our species has enjoyed and that holds out the greatest hope for continuing moral progress in the future. RNG: And if, our friends, you detect a flaw in this argument, just remember you'll be depending on reason to point it out. Thank you. SP: Thank you. (Applause)
si le raisonneur s'y complaît. La raison peut-elle forcer le raisonneur à vouloir moins de cruauté et de gaspillage ? RNG : Toute seule, la réponse est non, mais il suffit de peu pour basculer vers le oui. Deux conditions doivent être remplies : La première est que les raisonneurs doivent se préoccuper de leur propre bien-être. C'est l'un des intérêts qui doit être présent pour que la raison puisse fonctionner, il est évidemment présent en chacun de nous. Nous nous soucions tous passionnément de notre propre bien-être. La deuxième condition est que les raisonneurs fassent partie d'une communauté de raisonneurs capables d'affecter leur bien-être mutuel, de dialoguer entre eux, et de comprendre le raisonnement les uns des autres. C'est certainement le cas pour notre espèce, qui est grégaire et loquace, dotée de l'instinct du langage. SP : Eh bien, cela me paraît juste en théorie, mais les choses ont-elles fonctionné dans la pratique ? En particulier, cela peut-il expliquer le développement historique majeur dont j'ai parlé il y a environ cinq ans ici à TED ? À savoir, le fait que nous semblons devenir de plus en plus compatissants. Il y a des siècles, nos ancêtres brûlaient des chats vivants en guise de divertissement populaire. Les chevaliers se faisaient constamment la guerre en essayant de tuer le plus possible de paysans de l'autre. Les gouvernements exécutaient des gens pour des raisons frivoles, comme avoir volé un chou ou critiqué le jardin royal. Les exécutions étaient conçues pour être aussi longues et aussi douloureuses que possible, comme la crucifixion, l'éventration, le supplice de la roue. Les gens respectables avaient des esclaves. Malgré tous nos défauts, nous avons abandonné ces pratiques barbares. RNG : Pensez-vous que c'est la nature humaine qui a changé ? SP : Pas exactement. Je pense que nous entretenons des instincts donnant lieu à des éruptions de violence, comme la cupidité, le tribalisme, la vengeance, la domination et le sadisme. Nous avons aussi des instincts qui peuvent nous en éloigner, comme la maîtrise de soi, l'empathie, le sens de l'équité, ce qu'Abraham Lincoln appelait « les meilleurs anges de notre nature ». RNG : Si la nature humaine n'a pas changé, qu'est-ce qui a revigoré ces « meilleurs anges » ? SP : Eh bien, entre autres, notre cercle d'empathie s'est élargi. Il y a des années, nos ancêtres ne ressentaient de compassion que pour leur famille et pour les habitants de leur village. Avec le développement de l'alphabétisation et des voyages, les gens ont commencé à compatir avec des cercles de plus en plus larges, le clan, la tribu, la nation, la race, et peut-être, à terme, l'ensemble de l'humanité. RNG : Les scientifiques rigoureux peuvent-ils donner autant d'importance à la tendre empathie ? SP : Oui, c'est ce qu'ils font. Les neurophysiologistes ont découvert des neurones qui réagissent aux actions des autres personnes de la même façon dont ils réagissent aux nôtres. L'empathie apparaît tôt dans la vie, peut-être avant l'âge d'un an. Les livres sur l'empathie sont devenus des best-sellers, comme « La Civilisation Empathique » et « L'Âge de l'Empathie ». RNG : Je suis en faveur de l'empathie. Qui ne l'est pas ? Mais toute seule, c'est un outil peu convaincant pour être le moteur du progrès moral. Premièrement, elle est subjective par nature et s'oriente vers la famille directe, les bébés, et les animaux mignons et doux. Côté empathie, les étrangers moches peuvent aller se faire voir. Même nos meilleures tentatives pour étendre notre compassion à ceux qui ne sont pas directement liés à nous échouent à chaque fois, et cette triste vérité de la nature humaine a été soulignée par Adam Smith. AS : « Supposons que le vaste empire de Chine ait été soudainement avalé par un tremblement de terre, examinons de quelle manière l'Européen le plus humain réagirait en recevant la nouvelle de cette affreuse calamité. J'imagine que d'abord il exprimerait vivement la douleur que lui cause l'infortune d'un peuple entier, qu'il ferait quelques réflexions mélancoliques sur la précarité de la vie humaine, après avoir exprimé tout ce que ses sentiments humains lui inspirent, il retournerait à ses affaires ou ses plaisirs avec autant de facilité et de tranquillité que si une telle catastrophe n'avait pas eu lieu. Si on devait lui couper son petit doigt demain, il n'en dormirait pas de la nuit, mais pourvu qu'il ne les ait jamais vus, il ronflera d'un sommeil profond après la destruction d'une centaine de millions de ses frères. » SP : Si l'empathie ne suffit pas à nous rendre plus humain, quoi d'autre ? RNG : Vous n'avez pas mentionné ce qui pourrait être l'un de nos « meilleurs anges » les plus efficaces : la raison. La raison est musclée. C'est la raison qui donne l'impulsion pour élargir ce cercle d'empathie. Chacun des progrès sur le plan humain que vous avez mentionnés a commencé grâce à des penseurs qui ont trouvé des raisons pour lesquelles certaines pratiques étaient indéfendables. Ils ont démontré que la façon dont les gens traitaient tel groupe était illogique vu la manière dont ils avaient exigé d'être traités. SP : Vous dites donc que la raison peut faire changer l'avis des gens ? Ne se cramponnent-ils pas à n'importe quelle conviction pourvu qu'elle serve leurs intérêts ou se conforme à la culture dans laquelle ils ont grandi ? RNG : Voici un fait fascinant à propos de nous : Les contradictions nous dérangent, du moins quand nous sommes obligés de nous y confronter, ce qui est une autre façon de dire que nous sommes sensibles à la raison. Et si vous regardez l'histoire du progrès moral, vous pouvez tracer une corrélation directe entre les arguments raisonnés et les changements dans la façon dont nous pensons réellement. Il est arrivé très souvent qu'un penseur présente un argument pour montrer que telle ou telle pratique était indéfendable, irrationnelle, incompatible avec les valeurs déjà en vigueur. Que leur essai se répande, soit traduit en plusieurs langues, débattu dans les pubs, les cafés et les salons, et à des dîners, et influence les leaders, les législateurs, et l'opinion populaire. Puis leurs conclusions finissent par être intégrées au bon sens moral, effaçant les traces de l'argument initial qui nous avait fait arriver jusque là. Peu d'entre nous estiment nécessaires de nous lancer dans une argumentation philosophique rigoureuse pour expliquer pourquoi l'esclavage est mauvais, pareil pour les pendaisons publiques ou le fait de battre les enfants. À présent, ces choses semblent simplement mauvaises. Mais ces arguments précis ont dû être formulés à un moment, ils l'ont été dans les siècles passés. SP : Vous dites que les gens avaient besoin d'un argument détaillé pour comprendre pourquoi c'était un tout petit peu mal de brûler des hérétiques sur le bûcher ? RNG : Eh oui. Voici le théologien français Sébastien Castellion qui explique pourquoi. SC: « Calvin dit qu'il est sûr d'avoir raison, d'autres groupes religieux aussi. Qui sera juge ? Si les choses sont si sûres, pour qui le sont-elles ? Pour Calvin ? Pourquoi écrit-il autant de livres sur une vérité aussi évidente ? Compte tenu de l'incertitude, nous ne pouvons définir les hérétiques que comme ceux avec qui nous ne sommes pas d'accord. Du coup, si nous décidons de les tuer, la conséquence logique sera une guerre d'extermination, car chacun est sûr d'avoir raison. » SP : Pareil pour les punitions horribles comme le supplice de la roue ? RNG : L'interdiction, dans notre constitution, des châtiments cruels et inhabituels a été faite en réponse à une brochure distribuée en 1764 par le juriste italien Cesare Beccaria. CB: « À mesure que les supplices deviennent plus cruels, l'âme, semblable aux fluides qui se mettent toujours au niveau des objets qui les entourent, s'endurcit, après cent ans de punitions cruelles, le supplice de la roue ne provoque pas plus de peur que l'emprisonnement ne l'avait fait auparavant. Pour qu'une punition atteigne son objectif, il suffit que le mal qu'elle cause surpasse le bien que le coupable a retiré du crime, ce calcul doit prendre en compte la certitude de la sanction et la perte du bénéfice que le crime devait produire. Toute sévérité au-delà de ces limites devient superflue, donc tyrannique. » SP : Pourtant, les mouvements pacifistes ont été déclenchés par des manifestations gigantesques, par les mélodies accrocheuses des chanteurs de folk et les photographies déchirantes qui montraient le coût humain de la guerre. RNG : C'est certain, mais les mouvements pacifistes modernes remontent à une longue chaîne de penseurs qui ont fait valoir les raisons pour lesquelles nous devons mobiliser nos émotions contre la guerre, comme le père de la modernité, Érasme. Érasme : « Les avantages qui découlent de la paix se diffusent de tous côtés, bénéficient à un grand nombre de personnes, tandis que pour la guerre, si elle se finit bien pour l'un des partis, l'avantage qui en découle bénéficie à quelques personnes indignes d'en profiter. Un homme n'est en sécurité que parce qu'un autre a été détruit. Le trophée de l'un provient du pillage de la propriété d'un autre. Ce qui donne lieu à des réjouissances d'un côté est cause de deuil de l'autre. Tout ce qui est regrettable dans la guerre est extrêmement regrettable, à l'inverse, tout ce qui est considéré comme de la bonne fortune, est en fait une bonne fortune sauvage et cruelle, un bonheur mesquin dérivant son existence du malheur d'un autre. SP : Tout le monde sait que le mouvement pour l'abolition de l'esclavage était fondé sur la foi et les émotions. C'était un mouvement mené par les Quakers, il ne devint populaire que quand le roman de Harriet Beecher Stowe « La case de l'Oncle Tom » devint un best-seller. RNG : Mais le mouvement a été lancé un siècle auparavant. John Locke s'est rebellé contre tous les millénaires pendant lesquels cette pratique avait été considérée comme parfaitement naturelle. Il a fait valoir qu'elle était incompatible avec les principes de gouvernement rationnel. John Locke : « La liberté des hommes soumis à un gouvernement a pour la conduite de vie une certaine Règle commune à tout ceux de cette société, prescrite par le pouvoir législatif qui y a été formé, de sorte qu'ils puissent suivre et satisfaire leur volonté en toutes choses auxquelles cette Règle ne s'oppose pas, et qu'ils ne soient point sujets à la volonté, inconstante, incertaine, inconnue, arbitraire d'aucun autre homme, comme la liberté de la Nature consiste à n'être soumise à aucune autre loi qu'à celle de la Nature. » SP : Ces mots me disent quelque chose. Où les ai-je déjà lus ? Ah oui. Mary Astell : « Si la souveraineté absolue n'est pas nécessaire dans l'État, pourquoi le serait-elle dans la famille ? Si elle l'est dans la famille, pourquoi pas dans l'État puisqu'on ne peut arguer d'une raison pour l'un qui ne puisse s'appliquer avec encore plus de force pour l'autre ? Si tous les hommes naissent libres, comment se fait-il que toutes les femmes naissent esclaves, comme c'est le cas si l'on considère qu'être soumises à la volonté inconstante, incertaine imprévisible et arbitraire des hommes est la nature même de l'esclavage ? » RNG : Ce genre de cooptation, c'est exactement ce que fait la raison. Un mouvement pour l'élargissement des Droits de l'Homme en inspire un autre car leur logique est la même, une fois que cela est bien ancré dans toutes les têtes, il devient de plus en plus gênant d'ignorer les problèmes d'incohérence que cela cause. Dans les années 1960, le mouvement des droits civiques a inspiré les mouvements pour les droits des femmes, les droits des enfants, les droits des homosexuels, et même ceux des animaux. Deux siècles entiers auparavant, le penseur des Lumières Jeremy Bentham avait exposé le caractère indéfendable de pratiques alors habituelles, telles que la cruauté envers les animaux. JB: « La question n'est pas : peuvent-ils raisonner ? ni : peuvent-ils parler ? mais : peuvent-ils souffrir ? » RNG : La persécution des homosexuels. JB : « Pour ce qui est d'un mal causé directement, il est évident que [la pédérastie] ne produit de douleur chez personne. Au contraire, elle produit du plaisir. Les partenaires sont tous deux consentants. Si l'un des deux n'y consent pas, c'est là un crime totalement différent quant à la nature de ses effets : c'est une atteinte à la personne. C'est une sorte de viol. Mis à part celui de la douleur, le danger, si danger il y a, serait en grande partie celui de la contagion de l'exemple. Mais quelle est-elle ? Inciter autrui à se livrer aux mêmes pratiques ; Or cette pratique ne produit quelque douleur que ce soit chez personne. » SP : Pourtant, dans tous ces cas, il a fallu au moins un siècle pour que les arguments de ces grands penseurs soient réinjectés dans la société et influencent l'ensemble de la population. Cela fait un peu réfléchir à notre propre époque. Nous livrons-nous à des pratiques contre lesquelles il existe des arguments que tout le monde est capable de voir mais que nous continuons malgré tout à pratiquer ? RNG : Quand nos petits-enfants regarderont en arrière, seront-ils aussi consternés par certaines de nos pratiques que nous le sommes par l'esclavage, l'autodafé d'hérétiques, la violence conjugale et l'homophobie pratiqués par nos ancêtres ? SP : Je suis sûr que tout le monde ici pourrait trouver au moins un exemple. RNG : J'opte pour le mauvais traitement des animaux dans les élevages industriels. SP : L'emprisonnement des délinquants toxicomanes non violents et la tolérance des viols dans les prisons de notre pays. RNG : Lésiner sur les dons aux associations humanitaires qui sauvent des vies dans les pays en voie de développement. SP : La possession d'armes nucléaires. RNG : Le recours à la religion pour justifier ce qui est injustifiable autrement, comme l'interdiction de la contraception. SP : Pourquoi pas la religion en général ? RNG : Je ne me fais pas d'illusions. SP: Je suis maintenant convaincu que la raison est un « meilleur ange » qui mérite d'être reconnue à sa juste valeur pour le progrès moral que notre espèce a connu, c'est la raison qui est notre plus grand espoir de continuer notre progrès moral dans le futur. RNG : Et si, mes amis, vous détectez une faille dans cet argument, rappelez-vous juste que vous dépendrez de la raison pour la montrer. Merci. SP : Merci. (Applaudissements)